¬ Localised file for campaign descriptions

{CAESER_IN_GAUL_JULII_TITLE}House of Julii
{CAESER_IN_GAUL_JULII_DESCR}The year is 58 BC.\n\n
Gaius Julius Caesar has been appointed Pro-Consul of Rome and Governor of Cisalpine Gaul. He is responsible for the protection of the 'Friends of Rome'. These are the Gallic tribes who have agreed to be clients of the Republic: they give up their independence, but receive protection and the other benefits of Roman rule.\n\n
The Germanic Helvetii tribe, however, are not friends of Rome nor friends of the Gauls. They have begun to move south west into the lands occupied by the Aedui and Sequani peoples, two of the tribes who look to Rome and Caesar for protection.\n\n 
This is Caesar's chance. In the chaos of a war perhaps all of Gaul could be brought under Roman control. Any general who manages this would gain enormous political prestige at home, perhaps even enough to become master of Rome.\n\n 
This is your chance to match Caesar's achievements. Take the Roman Legions to victory in Gaul! 

{SONS_OF_MARS_JULII_TITLE}The House Of Julii
{SONS_OF_MARS_JULII_DESCR}You are the new leader (pater familias) of a young and upcoming noble (Patrician) family.\n\n
You have been given a military command by the Senate and People of Rome (SPQR) and must help forge a safe, strong and lasting empire in Italy.\n\n
Your first objectives are to repel a barbarian attack, just near Rome, and then move to take control of the town of Tarquinii, to the north west of Rome.\n\n
As your tutor will have told you, It is up to you to "seize the day" (carpe diem). 

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_JULII_TITLE}The House of Julii
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_JULII_DESCR}Rome is a place where tradition and history count for much. The legends of the city’s founding are important, and the powerful patrician families are directly descended from the first followers of Romulus. These heroic times demanded harsh, decisive action, and this is a tradition that the often-conservative Romans have maintained to this day. The Romans, including the Julii family, are people for whom politics and war are all or nothing affairs.\n\n 
The Fates have not always been kind to the Julii. They are a patrician family but one whose star has not always been in the ascendant. The family’s fortunes have declined and then risen over the centuries, so much so that they may almost be considered vaguely parvenu: upstarts newly arrived to wealth, power and authority. With the loss of position and status in the past, the other powerful factions of Rome look down (if only ever so slightly) on these ‘new men’ of Rome. The Julii have had to adjust to the realities of politics and power, and have cultivated their popularity with the common people. The rule of Rome may lie with the Senate for now, but the Julii know that the people also have a say in government. The Senate and the patrician classes need the plebeians to at least go along with their actions.\n\n 
This populist attitude to the common people puts the Julii at odds with the other great families. Which approach will lead to great power within Rome has still to be decided. The Julii have a commanding position in northern Italy that means they will be in vanguard of any struggle against barbarians. Success there can be translated into political power in Rome itself, as the mob always loves winners...

{EUROPA_270BC_JULII_TITLE}The House of Julii
{EUROPA_270BC_JULII_DESCR}Rome is a place where tradition and history count for much. The legends of the city’s founding are important, and the powerful patrician families are directly descended from the first followers of Romulus. These heroic times demanded harsh, decisive action, and this is a tradition that the often-conservative Romans have maintained to this day. The Romans, including the Julii family, are people for whom politics and war are all or nothing affairs.\n\n 
The Fates have not always been kind to the Julii. They are a patrician family but one whose star has not always been in the ascendant. The family’s fortunes have declined and then risen over the centuries, so much so that they may almost be considered vaguely parvenu: upstarts newly arrived to wealth, power and authority. With the loss of position and status in the past, the other powerful factions of Rome look down (if only ever so slightly) on these ‘new men’ of Rome. The Julii have had to adjust to the realities of politics and power, and have cultivated their popularity with the common people. The rule of Rome may lie with the Senate for now, but the Julii know that the people also have a say in government. The Senate and the patrician classes need the plebeians to at least go along with their actions.\n\n 
This populist attitude to the common people puts the Julii at odds with the other great families. Which approach will lead to great power within Rome has still to be decided. The Julii have a commanding position in northern Italy that means they will be in vanguard of any struggle against barbarians. Success there can be translated into political power in Rome itself, as the mob always loves winners...

{ROMAN_CAMPAIGN_JULII_TITLE}The Romans
{ROMAN_CAMPAIGN_JULII_DESCR}Having been sacked by the Gaul Brennus, Rome was shocked into expansion. They were determined to never again suffer the indignity of foreign intruders. To this end Rome had expanded her influence in the Italian Peninsular in a series of continuous and bloody wars. Her military had abandoned the old Greek methods of warfare and this had seen her take control over all of Latium and beyond.\n\n
However, Rome is now in greater danger than ever before. To the North, the Gallic barbarian hordes continue to raid Rome's lands; care should be taken to defend against these incursions. Any show of weakness and the Gauls may well decide to cross the border in force once again. \n\n
If the Gauls were not enough, to the South a far greater threat is looming. Roman spies report that Pyrrhus of Epirus, the cousin of Alexander the Great, has landed in Southern Italy in great force to aid the Greek colony of Tarentum. His army is formidable, the backbone being made up of veteran phalangites donated by the Macedonians, and also including strange and fearsome beasts. It will take all Rome's resources to defeat him. He must be stopped before he can establish a power base in the Greek colonies of Southern Italy.\n\n
The dangers before Rome will take all her effort to overcome, but sometimes the greatest dangers are the ones you cannot yet see. The Carthaginians continue to grow fat on their extensive trade networks, and now they are expanding into the resource rich lands of Southern Iberia. Soon Carthage will become too powerful for Rome, and therefore only be considered a threat. A threat cannot be allowed to grow.... something must be done about Carthage.



{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SCIPII_TITLE}The House of Scipii
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SCIPII_DESCR}The city of Rome had a violent foundation, one that mirrors much of the political and military infighting that happens between the great families of Rome. Romulus murdered Remus for jumping over the walls of the city, and then named himself King and renamed the city in his own honour. The patrician families of Rome claim descent from the adventurers, exiles and warriors Romulus recruited to help establish his city. The Scipii should be numbered among these ancient bloodlines.\n\n 
They are not, perhaps, of quite the first rank, although this in itself means that they are keen to prove themselves the equal of any other Romans, but they are certainly among the optimates, the aristocracy of the city, and have been for many generations. They are important people, used to the privileges of rank and the usages of power, both to further Rome’s ambitions and that of their own family. They have also produced able politicians and generals - the two go hand-in-hand in Rome, as political success rarely comes without success on the battlefield.\n\n 
They are, however, unusual in a couple of respects for a Roman family of the old ways. Firstly, they are extravagantly wealthy. Wealth is one thing, and this always brings power with it, but their use of wealth has sometimes surprised more conservative Romans (and Romans are nothing if not conservative). The Scipii also have a taste for Greek learning and culture, again something that surprises and concerns the conservative elements. Nevertheless, despite these un-Roman ways, the Scipii have the political skills and military competence to make their family greatest in Rome, and possibly the rulers of the known world. They may only directly control a couple of provinces in Italy and Sicily, but their ambitions are boundless... and realistic.

{EUROPA_270BC_SCIPII_TITLE}The House of Scipii
{EUROPA_270BC_SCIPII_DESCR}The city of Rome had a violent foundation, one that mirrors much of the political and military infighting that happens between the great families of Rome. Romulus murdered Remus for jumping over the walls of the city, and then named himself King and renamed the city in his own honour. The patrician families of Rome claim descent from the adventurers, exiles and warriors Romulus recruited to help establish his city. The Scipii should be numbered among these ancient bloodlines.\n\n 
They are not, perhaps, of quite the first rank, although this in itself means that they are keen to prove themselves the equal of any other Romans, but they are certainly among the optimates, the aristocracy of the city, and have been for many generations. They are important people, used to the privileges of rank and the usages of power, both to further Rome’s ambitions and that of their own family. They have also produced able politicians and generals - the two go hand-in-hand in Rome, as political success rarely comes without success on the battlefield.\n\n 
They are, however, unusual in a couple of respects for a Roman family of the old ways. Firstly, they are extravagantly wealthy. Wealth is one thing, and this always brings power with it, but their use of wealth has sometimes surprised more conservative Romans (and Romans are nothing if not conservative). The Scipii also have a taste for Greek learning and culture, again something that surprises and concerns the conservative elements. Nevertheless, despite these un-Roman ways, the Scipii have the political skills and military competence to make their family greatest in Rome, and possibly the rulers of the known world. They may only directly control a couple of provinces in Italy and Sicily, but their ambitions are boundless... and realistic.

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BRUTII_TITLE}The House of Brutii
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BRUTII_DESCR}The founding of Rome is shrouded in legend. Legend has it, for example, that the Romans can trace their ancestry back to Aeneas, the hero who escaped from the sack of Troy. The founding of Rome also involves violence and murder. Viewed in a certain light, much of subsequent Roman history can be seen as a continuation of these aggressive ways. Since this time, the Romans have kept fine traditions of warfare and high-stakes (or even murderous) politics.\n\n 
The Brutii know all about Roman politics. The founding of the Republic of Rome involves them closely, as they have been at the heart of the Republic for centuries and can even claim to the ‘Father of the Republic’ in the family. Lucius Junius Brutus pretended to be an idiot for years to avoid being killed by Lucius Tarquinius Superbus (Tarquin), the last king of Rome, and then managed to lead his people in expelling the hated king after the rape of Lucrece. Casting aside his idiot persona, he became one of the first praetors, a ruling office of the patrician class established before the consulship. Lucius Junius Brutus even had his own sons executed for plotting to restore the Tarquins to power. And that’s power politics played out to the bitter end.\n\n 
Membership of the patrician class is what sets the Brutii apart from the other Roman factions. They are counted among the old families of Rome, those related by blood, marriage or adoption to the founders. These are people who have always been important within the social hierarchy, people who would expect to have authority as a matter of course. This is why they now have control of southern Italy. The Brutii would not have expectations of power, however, if they had not been able to deliver the political and military skills that Rome requires. But now, perhaps, with Rome surrounded by enemies within and without, there is a chance to secure ultimate power, to become the new Imperators of a Roman Republic that extends throughout the known world…

{EUROPA_270BC_BRUTII_TITLE}The House of Brutii
{EUROPA_270BC_BRUTII_DESCR}The founding of Rome is shrouded in legend. Legend has it, for example, that the Romans can trace their ancestry back to Aeneas, the hero who escaped from the sack of Troy. The founding of Rome also involves violence and murder. Viewed in a certain light, much of subsequent Roman history can be seen as a continuation of these aggressive ways. Since this time, the Romans have kept fine traditions of warfare and high-stakes (or even murderous) politics.\n\n 
The Brutii know all about Roman politics. The founding of the Republic of Rome involves them closely, as they have been at the heart of the Republic for centuries and can even claim to the ‘Father of the Republic’ in the family. Lucius Junius Brutus pretended to be an idiot for years to avoid being killed by Lucius Tarquinius Superbus (Tarquin), the last king of Rome, and then managed to lead his people in expelling the hated king after the rape of Lucrece. Casting aside his idiot persona, he became one of the first praetors, a ruling office of the patrician class established before the consulship. Lucius Junius Brutus even had his own sons executed for plotting to restore the Tarquins to power. And that’s power politics played out to the bitter end.\n\n 
Membership of the patrician class is what sets the Brutii apart from the other Roman factions. They are counted among the old families of Rome, those related by blood, marriage or adoption to the founders. These are people who have always been important within the social hierarchy, people who would expect to have authority as a matter of course. This is why they now have control of southern Italy. The Brutii would not have expectations of power, however, if they had not been able to deliver the political and military skills that Rome requires. But now, perhaps, with Rome surrounded by enemies within and without, there is a chance to secure ultimate power, to become the new Imperators of a Roman Republic that extends throughout the known world…

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_CARTHAGE_TITLE}Carthaginians
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_CARTHAGE_DESCR}By tradition, Carthage was founded by Queen Dido who had fled from the city of Tyre in Phoenicia after her husband was killed by her brother. Even in the days of legend there was a link with Rome, because Aeneas of Troy, the father to the Romans, was the lover of Dido and then abandoned her. In her grief she killed herself, cursing Aeneas and his descendants as she died.\n\n 
Carthage - the name means ‘new town’ - continued to flourish, a Phoenician colony that outgrew and survived its parent land. The Phoenicians - and their successors the Carthaginians - must be credited with the invention of glass, the bireme galley and with being expert traders thanks to their superb navigational skills. Even before the Greeks reached the Western Mediterranean, Carthage was a superbly wealthy city, thanks to its mastery of the seas. Carthaginian colonies - colonies of the original Phoenician colony - now ring the sea (modern Barcelona is named after the famous Barca family). Carthage is a maritime power, with only a relatively small landowning class to provide military land power. This, however, does not matter as long as Carthage continues to be wealthy. Its coffers pay for mercenaries in abundance when the city needs to go to war.\n\n 
And it is this wealth, mastery of trade and expansion along the Mediterranean coast towards Italy that brings Carthage into direct confrontation with the newly rising power of Rome. Now, perhaps, it is time for Dido’s curse to have its full effects on the children of Aeneas...

{EUROPA_270BC_CARTHAGE_TITLE}Carthaginians
{EUROPA_270BC_CARTHAGE_DESCR}By tradition, Carthage was founded by Queen Dido who had fled from the city of Tyre in Phoenicia after her husband was killed by her brother. Even in the days of legend there was a link with Rome, because Aeneas of Troy, the father to the Romans, was the lover of Dido and then abandoned her. In her grief she killed herself, cursing Aeneas and his descendants as she died.\n\n 
Carthage - the name means ‘new town’ - continued to flourish, a Phoenician colony that outgrew and survived its parent land. The Phoenicians - and their successors the Carthaginians - must be credited with the invention of glass, the bireme galley and with being expert traders thanks to their superb navigational skills. Even before the Greeks reached the Western Mediterranean, Carthage was a superbly wealthy city, thanks to its mastery of the seas. Carthaginian colonies - colonies of the original Phoenician colony - now ring the sea (modern Barcelona is named after the famous Barca family). Carthage is a maritime power, with only a relatively small landowning class to provide military land power. This, however, does not matter as long as Carthage continues to be wealthy. Its coffers pay for mercenaries in abundance when the city needs to go to war.\n\n 
And it is this wealth, mastery of trade and expansion along the Mediterranean coast towards Italy that brings Carthage into direct confrontation with the newly rising power of Rome. Now, perhaps, it is time for Dido’s curse to have its full effects on the children of Aeneas...

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_EGYPT_TITLE}Egyptians
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_EGYPT_DESCR}After the death of Alexander the Great the empire he had created tottered and fell into disarray with remarkable speed. His empire was the largest ever seen, and the generals struggled against each other for the ultimate prize that none of them was quite strong enough to gain. The Diadochi, or Successors, were only strong enough to hold together fragments of Alexander’s empire.\n\n 
Egypt was one part of that empire and by anyone’s standards it is an ancient land. It is now ruled by Greek Pharaohs, the descendants of Ptolemy I, one of Alexander’s able generals. The Ptolemaic dynasty adjusted rapidly to Egyptian ways and adopted the royal ways of the Pharaohs - including divine status and marriage between the Pharaoh and his sister in each generation. All the succeeding Pharaohs have been called Ptolemy, and their sisters (more often than not) Cleopatra in the Egyptian fashion.\n\n 
Egypt, therefore, is a rich land under the new Pharaohs and a centre of learning for the Greek world. The Ptolemaic Pharaohs hold together a formidable kingdom and must be seen as a major power in the Eastern Mediterranean. Their potential in warfare against the other successor states is also impressive, and an aggressive Pharaoh could well expand Egypt’s boundaries far beyond the Nile valley...

{EUROPA_270BC_EGYPT_TITLE}Egyptians
{EUROPA_270BC_EGYPT_DESCR}After the death of Alexander the Great the empire he had created tottered and fell into disarray with remarkable speed. His empire was the largest ever seen, and the generals struggled against each other for the ultimate prize that none of them was quite strong enough to gain. The Diadochi, or Successors, were only strong enough to hold together fragments of Alexander’s empire.\n\n 
Egypt was one part of that empire and by anyone’s standards it is an ancient land. It is now ruled by Greek Pharaohs, the descendants of Ptolemy I, one of Alexander’s able generals. The Ptolemaic dynasty adjusted rapidly to Egyptian ways and adopted the royal ways of the Pharaohs - including divine status and marriage between the Pharaoh and his sister in each generation. All the succeeding Pharaohs have been called Ptolemy, and their sisters (more often than not) Cleopatra in the Egyptian fashion.\n\n 
Egypt, therefore, is a rich land under the new Pharaohs and a centre of learning for the Greek world. The Ptolemaic Pharaohs hold together a formidable kingdom and must be seen as a major power in the Eastern Mediterranean. Their potential in warfare against the other successor states is also impressive, and an aggressive Pharaoh could well expand Egypt’s boundaries far beyond the Nile valley...

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BRITANNIA_TITLE}Britons
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BRITANNIA_DESCR}The Britons are very similar to the Gauls - they come from the same robust Celtic stock after all, and many tribes can be found in Northern Gaul and in Britannia. The sea is no barrier. The Britons have their own sophisticated culture, trade and kingship flourish, and they have well-organised towns, a small but growing merchant class and age-old trading links to the world. The Phoenicians, for example, came to these islands for tin and lead.\n\n 
They also have a proud tradition as warriors. Britons are fierce fighters, and present a terrifying appearance to their foes. They dye themselves blue with woad, think nothing of danger, and often lime their hair into fantastical spikes, making them appear truly horrific. Perhaps a later Roman description of Britons as ‘Brittunculi’, wretched little Britons, is only partly contemptuous: it might equally be intended to make them less terrible. For the Britons can be terrible: their spirits are rarely broken by defeat or enslavement. They plot revenge, and then take it as brutally as possible. Their druidic religion can be savage to outsiders, demanding human sacrifice as a matter of course. Their traditional method of warfare involving fighting from light, highly manoeuvrable chariots can also put fear into many enemies. The noise alone is enough to scare many into flight.\n\n 
All in all, from their island home the Britons have much to feel confident about. They are a vibrant people, with a tradition of bravery in warfare and Gods who will aid and protect them. Protected by the moat of the sea from invasion, they can gaze out towards the mainland, and plan their conquests...

{EUROPA_270BC_BRITANNIA_TITLE}Britons
{EUROPA_270BC_BRITANNIA_DESCR}The Britons are very similar to the Gauls - they come from the same robust Celtic stock after all, and many tribes can be found in Northern Gaul and in Britannia. The sea is no barrier. The Britons have their own sophisticated culture, trade and kingship flourish, and they have well-organised towns, a small but growing merchant class and age-old trading links to the world. The Phoenicians, for example, came to these islands for tin and lead.\n\n 
They also have a proud tradition as warriors. Britons are fierce fighters, and present a terrifying appearance to their foes. They dye themselves blue with woad, think nothing of danger, and often lime their hair into fantastical spikes, making them appear truly horrific. Perhaps a later Roman description of Britons as ‘Brittunculi’, wretched little Britons, is only partly contemptuous: it might equally be intended to make them less terrible. For the Britons can be terrible: their spirits are rarely broken by defeat or enslavement. They plot revenge, and then take it as brutally as possible. Their druidic religion can be savage to outsiders, demanding human sacrifice as a matter of course. Their traditional method of warfare involving fighting from light, highly manoeuvrable chariots can also put fear into many enemies. The noise alone is enough to scare many into flight.\n\n 
All in all, from their island home the Britons have much to feel confident about. They are a vibrant people, with a tradition of bravery in warfare and Gods who will aid and protect them. Protected by the moat of the sea from invasion, they can gaze out towards the mainland, and plan their conquests...

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GAUL_TITLE}Gauls
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GAUL_DESCR}The Gauls are a confederation of many tribes who have successfully expanded their territorial range over centuries of migration. Their culture is vibrant, aggressive and proud, valuing courage in both their leaders and warriors.\n\n 
Do not mistake the Gallic people for simple barbarians. They are far from a simple people. Their culture is ancient. They have kings, coinage and developed trade. Their metal working skills are superb, easily the equal of their so-called civilized neighbours. Their towns are well organised and prosperous. Their culture is rich and they have Gods aplenty to keep them from harm. They have warriors aplenty to do harm unto others. They may lack the writing of the Greeks or Romans, but this does not make them savages.\n\n 
They are from the same robust Celtic stock as the Britons and indeed many of the same tribes can be found in both Northern Gaul and Britannia. The sea has been no barrier to their expansion. Like the Britons, the Gauls have a proud warrior tradition and are not people to lightly accept conquest or setbacks. They will fight, and fight hard, to preserve what is rightfully theirs, and to take new lands that could be rightfully theirs. A certain degree of bloody-mindedness also colours their druidic religion and warfare which many outsiders find deeply intimidating - headhunting does that to other people! 
The Gauls are a people with a great future, if they can find the space to expand successfully. They face many threats, from both ‘civilized’ people and other ‘barbarians’, but these threats can equally be seen as opportunities for greatness and glory. 

{EUROPA_270BC_GAUL_TITLE}Gauls
{EUROPA_270BC_GAUL_DESCR}The Gauls are a confederation of many tribes who have successfully expanded their territorial range over centuries of migration. Their culture is vibrant, aggressive and proud, valuing courage in both their leaders and warriors.\n\n 
Do not mistake the Gallic people for simple barbarians. They are far from a simple people. Their culture is ancient. They have kings, coinage and developed trade. Their metal working skills are superb, easily the equal of their so-called civilized neighbours. Their towns are well organised and prosperous. Their culture is rich and they have Gods aplenty to keep them from harm. They have warriors aplenty to do harm unto others. They may lack the writing of the Greeks or Romans, but this does not make them savages.\n\n 
They are from the same robust Celtic stock as the Britons and indeed many of the same tribes can be found in both Northern Gaul and Britannia. The sea has been no barrier to their expansion. Like the Britons, the Gauls have a proud warrior tradition and are not people to lightly accept conquest or setbacks. They will fight, and fight hard, to preserve what is rightfully theirs, and to take new lands that could be rightfully theirs. A certain degree of bloody-mindedness also colours their druidic religion and warfare which many outsiders find deeply intimidating - headhunting does that to other people! 
The Gauls are a people with a great future, if they can find the space to expand successfully. They face many threats, from both ‘civilized’ people and other ‘barbarians’, but these threats can equally be seen as opportunities for greatness and glory. 

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GERMANIA_TITLE}Germans
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GERMANIA_DESCR}The forests of Germania are dark and deep, and home to many brooding gods and malign forces. Some of this darkness, this menace, can be found in the people of the forests, men not easily tamed or turned to gentle pursuits. They are born to war, savage in battle, unforgiving of insults, implacable when feuding, and cruel in victory. Their gods are terrible and demand hideous sacrifices of men, women and children. This much, at least, the scribes of civilized lands believe to be true.\n\n 
The Germans are much like their Celtic neighbours, but with their own distinctive styles of dress, their own language and their own ways. They are a confederation of people who speak the same tongue and honour the same warlike and harsh gods rather than a nation. Their constant feuding amongst themselves make them distrusting of strangers and difficult allies. Warlords rise and fall among them almost continuously, and the difficult conditions in their homeland make sure that they have few large towns. Peace is almost unknown to them, except when it won with an axe or sword.\n\n 
All of this has produced a race of warriors second to none. The Germans may not be sophisticated fighters, but they are cunning, clever, and do not know the meaning of fear. Ambush and treachery they understand in full, along with vengeance and the importance of leaving no enemy alive. They are a vigorous people, a people who could be great across the whole of the world. All they need is leadership, and the chance to fight!

{EUROPA_270BC_GERMANIA_TITLE}Germans
{EUROPA_270BC_GERMANIA_DESCR}The forests of Germania are dark and deep, and home to many brooding gods and malign forces. Some of this darkness, this menace, can be found in the people of the forests, men not easily tamed or turned to gentle pursuits. They are born to war, savage in battle, unforgiving of insults, implacable when feuding, and cruel in victory. Their gods are terrible and demand hideous sacrifices of men, women and children. This much, at least, the scribes of civilized lands believe to be true.\n\n 
The Germans are much like their Celtic neighbours, but with their own distinctive styles of dress, their own language and their own ways. They are a confederation of people who speak the same tongue and honour the same warlike and harsh gods rather than a nation. Their constant feuding amongst themselves make them distrusting of strangers and difficult allies. Warlords rise and fall among them almost continuously, and the difficult conditions in their homeland make sure that they have few large towns. Peace is almost unknown to them, except when it won with an axe or sword.\n\n 
All of this has produced a race of warriors second to none. The Germans may not be sophisticated fighters, but they are cunning, clever, and do not know the meaning of fear. Ambush and treachery they understand in full, along with vengeance and the importance of leaving no enemy alive. They are a vigorous people, a people who could be great across the whole of the world. All they need is leadership, and the chance to fight!

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_MACEDON_TITLE}Macedonians
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_MACEDON_DESCR}After the death of Alexander the Great the empire he had created tottered and fell into disarray with remarkable speed. His empire was the largest ever seen, and the generals struggled against each other for the ultimate prize of being the new Alexander. Something that none of them was quite strong enough to attain. The Diadochi, or Successors, were only strong enough to hold together fragments of Alexander’s empire.\n\n 
Macedonia was the original home of Alexander, now ruled by the descendants of general Antigonus Cyclops or Antigonus the One-Eyed. The Macedonians are the proud inheritors of Alexander’s original kingdom. Macedonia itself, with parts of Greece as dependencies, has the potential to be a strong power once more. 
Although the empire may have slipped away from the Macedonians, they are still deadly warriors and fierce opponents. The Antigonid dynasty commands the respect of their people and has a strong military tradition. Macedonia has spent many long years struggling against the other Diadochi or ‘Successor’ states. This military might could equally be turned against other powers for domination of the eastern Mediterranean, Asia Minor and then, perhaps, the whole of the known world. A new Greek empire could arise and equal the achievements of Alexander...

{EUROPA_270BC_MACEDON_TITLE}Macedonians
{EUROPA_270BC_MACEDON_DESCR}After the death of Alexander the Great the empire he had created tottered and fell into disarray with remarkable speed. His empire was the largest ever seen, and the generals struggled against each other for the ultimate prize of being the new Alexander. Something that none of them was quite strong enough to attain. The Diadochi, or Successors, were only strong enough to hold together fragments of Alexander’s empire.\n\n 
Macedonia was the original home of Alexander, now ruled by the descendants of general Antigonus Cyclops or Antigonus the One-Eyed. The Macedonians are the proud inheritors of Alexander’s original kingdom. Macedonia itself, with parts of Greece as dependencies, has the potential to be a strong power once more. 
Although the empire may have slipped away from the Macedonians, they are still deadly warriors and fierce opponents. The Antigonid dynasty commands the respect of their people and has a strong military tradition. Macedonia has spent many long years struggling against the other Diadochi or ‘Successor’ states. This military might could equally be turned against other powers for domination of the eastern Mediterranean, Asia Minor and then, perhaps, the whole of the known world. A new Greek empire could arise and equal the achievements of Alexander...

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_PONTUS_TITLE}Kingdom of Pontus
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_PONTUS_DESCR}After the death of Alexander the Great the empire he had created tottered and fell into disarray with remarkable speed. His empire was the largest ever seen, and the generals struggled against each other for the ultimate prize that none of them was quite strong enough to attain. The Diadochi, or Successors, were only strong enough to hold together fragments of Alexander’s empire. Mithradates I, the son of Prince Mithradates of Cius, took advantage of this situation to establish a new kingdom of Pontus. He was not one of the Diadochi, but a freebooter who saw his chance and took it. In the confusion Mithradates rode to Pontus with six horsemen and made himself king. Mithradates was an able man, to say the least.\n\n 
Since then, Pontus has managed to maintain its independence from both Greek and Persian influences, even though the royal family have Persian roots. The kingdom has a good position on the Black Sea coast and the potential to expand into much of Asia Minor. Nearby lie the great trade routes from the east, a significant source of revenue. It is also home to many warlike peoples, a fact that could be exploited by expansionist rulers.

{EUROPA_270BC_PONTUS_TITLE}Kingdom of Pontus
{EUROPA_270BC_PONTUS_DESCR}After the death of Alexander the Great the empire he had created tottered and fell into disarray with remarkable speed. His empire was the largest ever seen, and the generals struggled against each other for the ultimate prize that none of them was quite strong enough to attain. The Diadochi, or Successors, were only strong enough to hold together fragments of Alexander’s empire. Mithradates I, the son of Prince Mithradates of Cius, took advantage of this situation to establish a new kingdom of Pontus. He was not one of the Diadochi, but a freebooter who saw his chance and took it. In the confusion Mithradates rode to Pontus with six horsemen and made himself king. Mithradates was an able man, to say the least.\n\n 
Since then, Pontus has managed to maintain its independence from both Greek and Persian influences, even though the royal family have Persian roots. The kingdom has a good position on the Black Sea coast and the potential to expand into much of Asia Minor. Nearby lie the great trade routes from the east, a significant source of revenue. It is also home to many warlike peoples, a fact that could be exploited by expansionist rulers.

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SELEUCID_TITLE}Seleucids
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SELEUCID_DESCR}The death of Alexander the Great brought dissolution to his empire almost before his corpse was cold. It may have been the largest empire the world had ever seen, but it proved fragile once the man himself was gone. His generals fought for control of what remained, but none of these Diadochi, or successors, was strong enough to be a new Alexander. The empire fragmented, and Seleucia was one of the splinter kingdoms, held together by the descendants of Seleucus, one of Alexander’s able lieutenants. Seleucus I came close to seizing the throne of Macedonia too, but was murdered before he could achieve this ambition. There have been tensions with Macedonia and Egypt ever since despite occasional marriages between the ruling houses of these states.\n\n 
The Seleucids hold the former Babylonian provinces of Alexander’s empire, an area of ancient cities and rich farmlands along the Tigris. (As an historical aside, the later Seleucid capital city of Ctesiphon is now under a suburb of Baghdad in Iraq; the earlier capital, Seleucia, was on the other river bank). This region also sits on the trade routes to the mysterious east, something that generates large revenues for the Seleucid kingdom. This, combined with the manpower and military expertise that are available, could make the Seleucids into masters of much of the known world. A Greek-Persian empire, combining the best of both systems as Seleucus tried to do, could be formidable indeed, and perhaps unstoppable.

{EUROPA_270BC_SELEUCID_TITLE}Seleucids
{EUROPA_270BC_SELEUCID_DESCR}The death of Alexander the Great brought dissolution to his empire almost before his corpse was cold. It may have been the largest empire the world had ever seen, but it proved fragile once the man himself was gone. His generals fought for control of what remained, but none of these Diadochi, or successors, was strong enough to be a new Alexander. The empire fragmented, and Seleucia was one of the splinter kingdoms, held together by the descendants of Seleucus, one of Alexander’s able lieutenants. Seleucus I came close to seizing the throne of Macedonia too, but was murdered before he could achieve this ambition. There have been tensions with Macedonia and Egypt ever since despite occasional marriages between the ruling houses of these states.\n\n 
The Seleucids hold the former Babylonian provinces of Alexander’s empire, an area of ancient cities and rich farmlands along the Tigris. (As an historical aside, the later Seleucid capital city of Ctesiphon is now under a suburb of Baghdad in Iraq; the earlier capital, Seleucia, was on the other river bank). This region also sits on the trade routes to the mysterious east, something that generates large revenues for the Seleucid kingdom. This, combined with the manpower and military expertise that are available, could make the Seleucids into masters of much of the known world. A Greek-Persian empire, combining the best of both systems as Seleucus tried to do, could be formidable indeed, and perhaps unstoppable.

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BRUTII_TITLE}The House of Brutii
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BRUTII_DESCR}The founding of Rome is shrouded in legend. Legend has it, for example, that the Romans can trace their ancestry back to Aeneas, the hero who escaped from the sack of Troy. The founding of Rome also involves violence and murder. Viewed in a certain light, much of subsequent Roman history can be seen as a continuation of these aggressive ways. Since this time, the Romans have kept fine traditions of warfare and high-stakes (or even murderous) politics.\n\n 
The Brutii know all about Roman politics. The founding of the Republic of Rome involves them closely, as they have been at the heart of the Republic for centuries and can even claim to have the ‘Father of the Republic’ in their family. Lucius Junius Brutus pretended to be an idiot for years to avoid being killed by Lucius Tarquinius Superbus (Tarquin), the last king of Rome, and then managed to lead his people in expelling the hated king after the rape of Lucrece. Casting aside his idiot persona, he became one of the first praetors, a ruling office of the patrician class established before the consulship. Lucius Junius Brutus even had his own sons executed for plotting to restore the Tarquins to power...that’s power politics played out to the bitter end. 
Membership of the patrician class is what sets the Brutii apart from the other Roman factions. They are counted among the old families of Rome, those related by blood, marriage or adoption to the founders. These are people who have always been important within the social hierarchy, people who would expect to have authority as a matter of course. This is why they now have control of southern Italy. The Brutii would not have expectations of power, however, if they had not been able to deliver the political and military skills that Rome requires. But now, perhaps, with Rome surrounded by enemies within and without, there is a chance to secure ultimate power, to become the new Imperators of a Roman Republic that extends throughout the known world…

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GERMANIA_TITLE}Germans
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GERMANIA_DESCR}The forests of Germania are dark and deep, and home to many brooding gods and malign forces. Some of this darkness, this menace, can be found in the people of the forests, men not easily tamed or turned to gentle pursuits. They are born to war, savage in battle, unforgiving of insults, implacable when feuding, and cruel in victory. Their gods are terrible and demand hideous sacrifices of men, women and children. This much, at least, the scribes of civilized lands believe to be true.\n\n 
The Germans are much like their Celtic neighbours, but with their own distinctive styles of dress, their own language and their own ways. They are a confederation of people who speak the same tongue and honour the same warlike and harsh gods rather than a nation. Their constant feuding amongst themselves make them distrusting of strangers and difficult allies. Warlords rise and fall among them almost continuously, and the difficult conditions in their homeland make sure that they have few large towns. Peace is almost unknown to them, except when won with an axe or sword.\n\n 
All of this has produced a race of warriors second to none. The Germans may not be sophisticated fighters, but they are cunning, clever, and do not know the meaning of fear. Ambush and treachery they understand in full, along with vengeance and the importance of leaving no enemy alive. They are a vigorous people, a people who could be great across the whole of the world. All they need is leadership, and the chance to fight!

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_PARTHIA_TITLE}Parthians
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_PARTHIA_DESCR}The Parthians are a nomadic people who conquered and settled in the area near the Caspian Sea in the 4th century BC as part of the Dahae confederation. Since that time the Parthians, under their Arsacid rulers (named after King Arsaces I), have fiercely maintained their independence. The Seleucids have, from time to time, claimed to be the overlords of Parthia and, from time to time, have actually been strong enough to try and enforce their claim. This is not something that endears the Seleucid Empire to the Parthian kings.\n\n 
The Parthians have the potential to be a great power – perhaps a great Empire – as they sit close to or astride the main trade routes from the east to the Mediterranean. The wealth of the world flows through these lands: a fortune that could pay for any army that an ambitious king could imagine. This wealth is there for the taking, for the people with the will to stretch out their hands and grasp it. Historically, the Parthians managed to become a great power, and fight off the advance of Rome into their heartlands.\n\n 
To the north are the barbarian steppes, peopled by fierce tribes who require watching. To the west, though, lie the Seleucid Empire and the lands of Alexander’s successors. These too are ruled by ambitious men. And beyond them, the rising power of Rome, and the traders of Carthage. Perhaps common cause could be made with them, for a while…

{EUROPA_270BC_PARTHIA_TITLE}Parthians
{EUROPA_270BC_PARTHIA_DESCR}The Parthians are a nomadic people who conquered and settled in the area near the Caspian Sea in the 4th century BC as part of the Dahae confederation. Since that time the Parthians, under their Arsacid rulers (named after King Arsaces I), have fiercely maintained their independence. The Seleucids have, from time to time, claimed to be the overlords of Parthia and, from time to time, have actually been strong enough to try and enforce their claim. This is not something that endears the Seleucid Empire to the Parthian kings.\n\n 
The Parthians have the potential to be a great power – perhaps a great Empire – as they sit close to or astride the main trade routes from the east to the Mediterranean. The wealth of the world flows through these lands: a fortune that could pay for any army that an ambitious king could imagine. This wealth is there for the taking, for the people with the will to stretch out their hands and grasp it. Historically, the Parthians managed to become a great power, and fight off the advance of Rome into their heartlands.\n\n 
To the north are the barbarian steppes, peopled by fierce tribes who require watching. To the west, though, lie the Seleucid Empire and the lands of Alexander’s successors. These too are ruled by ambitious men. And beyond them, the rising power of Rome, and the traders of Carthage. Perhaps common cause could be made with them, for a while…

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GREEK_CITIES_TITLE}Greeks
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_GREEK_CITIES_DESCR}The Greeks have a right to be proud. They are the fathers of democracy and reason, bringers of civilization and culture to the lands around the Mediterranean. There are few corners of the known world that have not felt the tread of a Greek army, or been graced by the magnificence of Greek architecture. The world is only the way it is because Greeks fought off the despots of Persia, and because Alexander led Greeks to the ends of the earth!\n\nNow, however, the Greeks are reduced in power, and largely confined to their original homelands. A loose confederation of city-states and petty kingdoms, held together by a need for mutual protection, is what remains. But there could still be greatness within Greece. The same blood that once defied Xerxes still runs in the veins of Athenians, Thebans, Spartans and the rest. The men of Greece still value their independence and civilization, and could still take this back to every corner of the world.\n\n 
Perhaps now is the time for the Greeks to be great again. Alexander’s heirs still fight amongst themselves for the spoils of empire. The rising power of Rome has yet to break out of the confines of Italy – they face the Carthaginians as rivals. To the north, the semi-civilized Dacians and other barbarians are surely no threat to civilized men, and Greeks have never bowed the knee to Eastern despots! 

{EUROPA_270BC_GREEK_CITIES_TITLE}Greeks
{EUROPA_270BC_GREEK_CITIES_DESCR}The Greeks have a right to be proud. They are the fathers of democracy and reason, bringers of civilization and culture to the lands around the Mediterranean. There are few corners of the known world that have not felt the tread of a Greek army, or been graced by the magnificence of Greek architecture. The world is only the way it is because Greeks fought off the despots of Persia, and because Alexander led Greeks to the ends of the earth!\n\nNow, however, the Greeks are reduced in power, and largely confined to their original homelands. A loose confederation of city-states and petty kingdoms, held together by a need for mutual protection, is what remains. But there could still be greatness within Greece. The same blood that once defied Xerxes still runs in the veins of Athenians, Thebans, Spartans and the rest. The men of Greece still value their independence and civilization, and could still take this back to every corner of the world.\n\n 
Perhaps now is the time for the Greeks to be great again. Alexander’s heirs still fight amongst themselves for the spoils of empire. The rising power of Rome has yet to break out of the confines of Italy – they face the Carthaginians as rivals. To the north, the semi-civilized Dacians and other barbarians are surely no threat to civilized men, and Greeks have never bowed the knee to Eastern despots! 

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BRITANNIA_TITLE}Britons
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_BRITANNIA_DESCR}The Britons are very similar to the Gauls - they come from the same robust Celtic stock after all, and many tribes can be found in Northern Gaul and in Britannia. The sea is no barrier. The Britons have their own sophisticated culture, within which trade and kingship flourish, and they have well-organised towns, a small but growing merchant class and age-old trading links to the world. The Phoenicians, for example, came to these islands for tin and lead.\n\n 
They also have a proud tradition as warriors. Britons are fierce fighters, and present a terrifying appearance to their foes. They dye themselves blue with woad, think nothing of danger, and often lime their hair into fantastical spikes, making them appear truly horrific. Perhaps a later Roman description of Britons as ‘Brittunculi’, wretched little Britons, is only partly contemptuous: it might equally be intended to make them less terrible. For the Britons can be terrible: their spirits are rarely broken by defeat or enslavement. They plot revenge, and then take it as brutally as possible. Their druidic religion can be savage to outsiders, demanding human sacrifice as a matter of course. Their traditional method of warfare involving fighting from light, highly manoeuvrable chariots can also put fear into many enemies. The noise alone is enough to scare many into flight.\n\n 
All in all, from their island home the Britons have much to feel confident about. They are a vibrant people, with a tradition of bravery in warfare and Gods who will aid and protect them. Protected by the moat of the sea from invasion, they can gaze out towards the mainland, and plan their conquests...

{EUROPA_270BC_BRITANNIA_TITLE}Britons
{EUROPA_270BC_BRITANNIA_DESCR}The Britons are very similar to the Gauls - they come from the same robust Celtic stock after all, and many tribes can be found in Northern Gaul and in Britannia. The sea is no barrier. The Britons have their own sophisticated culture, within which trade and kingship flourish, and they have well-organised towns, a small but growing merchant class and age-old trading links to the world. The Phoenicians, for example, came to these islands for tin and lead.\n\n 
They also have a proud tradition as warriors. Britons are fierce fighters, and present a terrifying appearance to their foes. They dye themselves blue with woad, think nothing of danger, and often lime their hair into fantastical spikes, making them appear truly horrific. Perhaps a later Roman description of Britons as ‘Brittunculi’, wretched little Britons, is only partly contemptuous: it might equally be intended to make them less terrible. For the Britons can be terrible: their spirits are rarely broken by defeat or enslavement. They plot revenge, and then take it as brutally as possible. Their druidic religion can be savage to outsiders, demanding human sacrifice as a matter of course. Their traditional method of warfare involving fighting from light, highly manoeuvrable chariots can also put fear into many enemies. The noise alone is enough to scare many into flight.\n\n 
All in all, from their island home the Britons have much to feel confident about. They are a vibrant people, with a tradition of bravery in warfare and Gods who will aid and protect them. Protected by the moat of the sea from invasion, they can gaze out towards the mainland, and plan their conquests...
                                             
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_ARMENIA_TITLE}Armenia
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_ARMENIA_DESCR} DIFFICULTY: Very Hard\n\nThe Armenians are a difficult faction in DarthMod 7.0 because they must contend with the nearby empires of both Parthia and the Seleucids, while raising a very expensive army. It would not be advisable to take on both of these likely enemies at once.\n\n  Instead, it may be wiser to ally with another small kingdom in the vicinity: Pontus.  With the support gained from each other's forces, you may very well be able to put up a fight against the much larger, and more dominant, empires of the south and east.  Of course, choosing this course of action means that you will eventually have to deal with a Pontic threat.\n\nAlternatively, you could choose to strike at Pontus in the beginning, and claim their mountainous provinces for your own.  Doing this risks the exposure of your back to the Parthians and Seleucids, both of which would be eager to swallow up a small kingdom such as yours while you were busy waging a petty war with a petty empire...

{EUROPA_270BC_ARMENIA_TITLE}Armenia
{EUROPA_270BC_ARMENIA_DESCR} DIFFICULTY: Very Hard\n\nThe Armenians are a difficult faction in DarthMod 7.0 because they must contend with the nearby empires of both Parthia and the Seleucids, while raising a very expensive army. It would not be advisable to take on both of these likely enemies at once.\n\n  Instead, it may be wiser to ally with another small kingdom in the vicinity: Pontus.  With the support gained from each other's forces, you may very well be able to put up a fight against the much larger, and more dominant, empires of the south and east.  Of course, choosing this course of action means that you will eventually have to deal with a Pontic threat.\n\nAlternatively, you could choose to strike at Pontus in the beginning, and claim their mountainous provinces for your own.  Doing this risks the exposure of your back to the Parthians and Seleucids, both of which would be eager to swallow up a small kingdom such as yours while you were busy waging a petty war with a petty empire...

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_DACIA_TITLE}Dacia
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_DACIA_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Hard\n\nThe Dacians are faced with several difficult tasks, not least of them being the Roman threat directly across the Adriatic Sea.  They are surrounded on all sides by potential enemies; Thrace, Macedonians, Sarmatians, Germans, Romans.  It will be imperative to ally to at least a few of these seperate civilisations, as to be embroiled in a war on all fronts would spell certain doom. \n\n To the north are uninhabited lands that may prove worthwhile in conquering, although their fertility is questionable.  To the northeast are the Sarmatians, great horsemen.  Combat against them may prove difficult without proper cavalry of your own.\n\nMacedon and Thrace are to your east, and if left alone, may simply wear themselves out fighting one another.  Macedon will surely attempt war with the Greeks, and by their own mistakes may give themselves up to your conquest.\n\nBut your greatest threat, later in the game, has to be the Roman one.  Assuming they survive their initial wars with Greece and Carthage, they will eventually sail across the sea looking for new lands, and they will find them along the coast.  If these are taken early by yourself, it may serve to protect you from their advances, but they may also decide to take them anyways...

{EUROPA_270BC_DACIA_TITLE}Dacia
{EUROPA_270BC_DACIA_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Hard\n\nThe Dacians are faced with several difficult tasks, not least of them being the Roman threat directly across the Adriatic Sea.  They are surrounded on all sides by potential enemies; Thrace, Macedonians, Sarmatians, Germans, Romans.  It will be imperative to ally to at least a few of these seperate civilisations, as to be embroiled in a war on all fronts would spell certain doom. \n\n To the north are uninhabited lands that may prove worthwhile in conquering, although their fertility is questionable.  To the northeast are the Sarmatians, great horsemen.  Combat against them may prove difficult without proper cavalry of your own.\n\nMacedon and Thrace are to your east, and if left alone, may simply wear themselves out fighting one another.  Macedon will surely attempt war with the Greeks, and by their own mistakes may give themselves up to your conquest.\n\nBut your greatest threat, later in the game, has to be the Roman one.  Assuming they survive their initial wars with Greece and Carthage, they will eventually sail across the sea looking for new lands, and they will find them along the coast.  If these are taken early by yourself, it may serve to protect you from their advances, but they may also decide to take them anyways...

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_NUMIDIA_TITLE}Numidia
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_NUMIDIA_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Very Hard\n\nThe Numidians could very well be the most difficult faction to play as in DarthMod 7.0.  Beware, they are only for the veterans amongst us.\n\nPlaying the Numidians is a tough proposition.  Their lands are poor, being mostly in the desert, and they have to contend with the might of Carthage to boot.  Your best option is to consolidate your small selection of provinces, and grow them to a higher level before attempting major conquest.  Ally with those you can, and only turn on them when you are positive you are ready.  If you strike too soon, you may be overwhelmed within a few years.\n\nYou have the benefit of being able to expand across the Strait of Gibraltar into the Iberian peninsula.  You may be able to attack the native Spanish tribes, while keeping the African mainland as a stronghold and natural barrier against their incursions.  But be wary.  To the north are the mighty Carthaginians, and they will surely not put up with a pesky neighbour for long.\n\nIt may be wise to first become allies with them, before turning your mind to other pursuits.  To the east of your farthest province lies the aggressive Ptolemaic Empire. It will be tough marching recruits across the desert to meet any possible threats that arise from them, so tread carefully in your dealings...

{EUROPA_270BC_NUMIDIA_TITLE}Numidia
{EUROPA_270BC_NUMIDIA_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Very Hard\n\nThe Numidians could very well be the most difficult faction to play as in DarthMod 7.0.  Beware, they are only for the veterans amongst us.\n\nPlaying the Numidians is a tough proposition.  Their lands are poor, being mostly in the desert, and they have to contend with the might of Carthage to boot.  Your best option is to consolidate your small selection of provinces, and grow them to a higher level before attempting major conquest.  Ally with those you can, and only turn on them when you are positive you are ready.  If you strike too soon, you may be overwhelmed within a few years.\n\nYou have the benefit of being able to expand across the Strait of Gibraltar into the Iberian peninsula.  You may be able to attack the native Spanish tribes, while keeping the African mainland as a stronghold and natural barrier against their incursions.  But be wary.  To the north are the mighty Carthaginians, and they will surely not put up with a pesky neighbour for long.\n\nIt may be wise to first become allies with them, before turning your mind to other pursuits.  To the east of your farthest province lies the aggressive Ptolemaic Empire. It will be tough marching recruits across the desert to meet any possible threats that arise from them, so tread carefully in your dealings...

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SCYTHIA_TITLE}Sarmatia
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SCYTHIA_DESCR} DIFFICULTY: Hard\n\nThe Sarmatians have always been difficult to play as.  Their provinces are on the northern fringe of the game map, and their infantry units are extremely limited.  They require a different type of game-play to be successful.\n\nAs the Sarmatians, you'll be faced with tough choices very early in the game.  With income low, you must decide quickly on where to expand with your horsemen.  To the east lies the Black Sea, and beyond that the rich lands of Parthia.  But to wage war with them may be too much for the Sarmatians early on, as their rate of income is very low compared to other factions.\n\nTo the south are their historical allies of Dacia, and near to them, the Thracians.  A civilisation such as this may be easy pickings for a clever general who utilizes his horse archers correctly.  To the west are the Germanic peoples, and many towns of independents.  There may be room for expansion, but the fertility of the lands is questionable, and the thick forests may tactically prove disasterous to the wide open type of combat your horsemen prefer.\n\nThese very warriors will be the key to your success.  Use these mounted soldiers well, and you may prove unstoppable.  If not, your choice of infantry will limit you...

{EUROPA_270BC_SCYTHIA_TITLE}Sarmatia
{EUROPA_270BC_SCYTHIA_DESCR} DIFFICULTY: Hard\n\nThe Sarmatians have always been difficult to play as.  Their provinces are on the northern fringe of the game map, and their infantry units are extremely limited.  They require a different type of game-play to be successful.\n\nAs the Sarmatians, you'll be faced with tough choices very early in the game.  With income low, you must decide quickly on where to expand with your horsemen.  To the east lies the Black Sea, and beyond that the rich lands of Parthia.  But to wage war with them may be too much for the Sarmatians early on, as their rate of income is very low compared to other factions.\n\nTo the south are their historical allies of Dacia, and near to them, the Thracians.  A civilisation such as this may be easy pickings for a clever general who utilizes his horse archers correctly.  To the west are the Germanic peoples, and many towns of independents.  There may be room for expansion, but the fertility of the lands is questionable, and the thick forests may tactically prove disasterous to the wide open type of combat your horsemen prefer.\n\nThese very warriors will be the key to your success.  Use these mounted soldiers well, and you may prove unstoppable.  If not, your choice of infantry will limit you...

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SPAIN_TITLE}Spain
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_SPAIN_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Hard\n\nSpain are in a potentially explosive situation.  They are squished between the Carthaginian colonies, and the Gallic tribes to the north.  By allying with one, and warring with the other, they may be able to end up with Iberia completely to themselves.\n\nSpainish are the native people of the peninsula they currently inhabit, and it's only fitting that they destroy those who have upset the natural balance.  By claiming Iberia for yourself, you will not only be consolidating your burgeoning empire behind the protective wall of the Pyrenees, but you will also be turning into an economic power house with the rich gold and silver mines that are scattered throughout the hills and mountains.\n\nYour best course of action may be choosing to war with the colonists of Carthage. They will likely be embroiled in a war across the sea with the Romans, and a small side show against some 'barbarians' performing guerrilla tactics will not be very popular back home in their Senate. \n\n  By keeping them on their toes and embroiled in a war of short strikes, they will surely be defeated within a brief period of time.  Choosing to go north against the Gauls first may not prove as fruitful, as you will leave your back exposed to treacherous Carthaginian attacks...

{EUROPA_270BC_SPAIN_TITLE}Spain
{EUROPA_270BC_SPAIN_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Hard\n\nSpain are in a potentially explosive situation.  They are squished between the Carthaginian colonies, and the Gallic tribes to the north.  By allying with one, and warring with the other, they may be able to end up with Iberia completely to themselves.\n\nSpainish are the native people of the peninsula they currently inhabit, and it's only fitting that they destroy those who have upset the natural balance.  By claiming Iberia for yourself, you will not only be consolidating your burgeoning empire behind the protective wall of the Pyrenees, but you will also be turning into an economic power house with the rich gold and silver mines that are scattered throughout the hills and mountains.\n\nYour best course of action may be choosing to war with the colonists of Carthage. They will likely be embroiled in a war across the sea with the Romans, and a small side show against some 'barbarians' performing guerrilla tactics will not be very popular back home in their Senate. \n\n  By keeping them on their toes and embroiled in a war of short strikes, they will surely be defeated within a brief period of time.  Choosing to go north against the Gauls first may not prove as fruitful, as you will leave your back exposed to treacherous Carthaginian attacks...

{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_THRACE_TITLE}Thrace
{IMPERIAL_CAMPAIGN_THRACE_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Hard\n\nThrace are also in a potentially explosive situation.  They are squished between the Macedon colonies, and the Saramations to the north.  By allying with one, and warring with the other, you may be able to end up with most of coast to yourselves
\n\nThrace are small to begin with only holding only Tylis,Byzamnium and Campus Getae. With only 500 men in your only army. You must first build up your ecomany and make trade routes and allainces with fellow cilivizons. Your also land locked expect to the west, with ocean there. Your Main threats with me sythia, dacia, macedon and pontus... 

{EUROPA_270BC_THRACE_TITLE}Thrace
{EUROPA_270BC_THRACE_DESCR}DIFFICULTY: Hard\n\nThrace are also in a potentially explosive situation.  They are squished between the Macedon colonies, and the Saramations to the north.  By allying with one, and warring with the other, you may be able to end up with most of coast to yourselves
\n\nThrace are small to begin with only holding only Tylis,Byzamnium and Campus Getae. With only 500 men in your only army. You must first build up your ecomany and make trade routes and allainces with fellow cilivizons. Your also land locked expect to the west, with ocean there. Your Main threats with me sythia, dacia, macedon and pontus...



